<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-14T05:05:23+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Theory @ Georgetown</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Borders, Debordering, and Algebraic Complexity</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Pranjal-Dutta/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Borders, Debordering, and Algebraic Complexity"/><published>2025-11-07T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-07T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Pranjal-Dutta</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Pranjal-Dutta/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Pranjal Dutta November 7, 2025. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>I will briefly introduce Valiant’s framework for algebraic complexity—VP vs. VNP (determinant vs. permanent)—and the associated border variants. Border complexity – central to algebraic complexity and to Geometric Complexity Theory (GCT) – captures polynomials lying in the Zariski closure of low-complexity classes; equivalently, those obtainable as limits (degenerations) of efficient computations. Notably, the best upper bounds on the matrix-multiplication exponent come via low border tensor rank. Debordering is the task of proving an upper bound on some non-border complexity measure in terms of a border complexity measure, thereby eliminating limits. The talk will focus on two concrete toy models defined by Waring rank and Chow rank, as well as their border versions. I will survey recent qualitative debordering results, compare structural behaviors of border vs. non-border measures in these models, and outline some open problems. For a detailed survey, refer to the recent article: https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13049 No prior knowledge of algebraic complexity, or advanced mathematics is required.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fall-2025"/><category term="algebraic"/><category term="complexity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pranjal Dutta]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Replicable Reinforcement Learning</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Jessica-Sorrell/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Replicable Reinforcement Learning"/><published>2025-03-21T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-21T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Jessica-Sorrell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Jessica-Sorrell/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Jessica Sorrell March 21, 2025. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>The replicability crisis in the social, behavioral, and data sciences has led to the formulation of algorithmic frameworks for replicability – i.e., a requirement that an algorithm produce identical outputs (with high probability) when run on two different samples from the same underlying distribution. In control problems such as reinforcement learning, where an agent’s actions can change the underlying distribution, such stability guarantees can be challenging to obtain. We will introduce provably replicable algorithms for reinforcement learning in tabular MDPs, which guarantee that even in stochastic environments, two independent runs of a learning algorithm will converge on precisely the same policy with high probability.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="spring-2025"/><category term="reinforcement"/><category term="learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jessica Sorrell]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Oblivious Classes Revisited: Lower Bounds and Hierarchies</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Karthik/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oblivious Classes Revisited: Lower Bounds and Hierarchies"/><published>2025-02-07T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-07T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Karthik</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2025/Karthik/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Karthik Gajulapalli February 7, 2025. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>In this talk we will look at the oblivious counter parts of some popular complexity classes.  We will see the resolution of two very interesting open problems: 1) A fixed polynomial circuit lower bound for a uniform class contained in P/poly 2) A uniform hierarchy theorem of a semantic class that contains BPP.</p> <p>Our results follow via the powerful range avoidance framework, and the notion of  “uniformly-sparse extensions” , our main technical contribution, that might be of independent interest.</p>]]></content><author><name>Karthik Gajulapalli</name></author><category term="spring-2025"/><category term="computational"/><category term="complexity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Speaker ]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can we bypass the curse of dimensionality in private data analysis?</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Eliad-Tsfadia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can we bypass the curse of dimensionality in private data analysis?"/><published>2024-11-15T16:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-15T16:15:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Eliad-Tsfadia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Eliad-Tsfadia/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Eliad Tsfadia November 14, 2025. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Differentially private (DP) algorithms typically exhibit a significant dependence on the dimensionality of their input, as their error or sample complexity tends to grow polynomially with the dimension. This cost of dimensionality is inherent in many problems, as Bun, Ullman, and Vadhan (STOC 2014) showed that any method that achieves lower error rates is vulnerable to tracing attacks (also known as, membership inference attacks). Unfortunately, such a cost is usually too high in many real-world scenarios like training large neural networks where the number of parameters (the ambient dimension) is very high.</p> <p>On the positive side, the lower bounds do not rule out the possibility of reducing the error rates for “easy” inputs. But what are “easy” inputs? And, how likely is it to see such inputs in real-world scenarios? In this talk, I’ll present a few ways to quantify “easiness” for the fundamental task of private averaging and support them with upper and lower bounds. In particular, I’ll show types of properties that are sufficient and necessary for eliminating the polynomial dependency in the dimension. I’ll end the talk by presenting several future research directions.</p> <p>The talk is mainly based on the following three papers: (1) FriendlyCore https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.10132 (joint with Edith Cohen, Haim Kaplan, Yishay Mansour, and Uri Stemmer, ICML 2022), (2) https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07604 (joint with Naty Peter and Jonathan Ullman, COLT 2024), (3) https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06465 (NeurIPS 2024)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fall-2024"/><category term="private"/><category term="data"/><category term="analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Eliad Tsfadia]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time-space tradeoffs in cryptography</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/itai-dinur/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time-space tradeoffs in cryptography"/><published>2024-11-08T16:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-08T16:15:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/itai-dinur</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/itai-dinur/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Itai Dinur November 8, 2024. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>A time-space tradeoff for a problem is a curve that quantifies the difficulty of solving it in terms of both the time complexity and the space complexity. Such tradeoffs play a significant role in algorithmic research, as they provide a more realistic estimate of how difficult it is to solve a problem than merely considering time complexity.</p> <p>In this talk I will discuss time-space tradeoff algorithms and lower bounds for important problems in the domain of cryptography, under various computational models. These problems include distinguishing a uniformly chosen permutation from a uniformly chosen function and finding multiple collisions in a uniformly chosen function. I will also discuss barriers that prevent us from proving that certain time-space algorithms are optimal.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fall-2024"/><category term="cryptography"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Itai Dinur]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beating Bellman-Ford: Faster Single-Source Shortest Paths with Negative Weights</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Jeremy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beating Bellman-Ford: Faster Single-Source Shortest Paths with Negative Weights"/><published>2024-11-07T18:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T18:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Jeremy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Jeremy/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker</h3> <p>Jeremy Fineman November 7, 2024.</p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Professor Fineman will present a talk on his paper “Beating Bellman-Ford: Faster Single-Source Shortest Paths with Negative Weights” which received a Best Paper Award at the 2024 ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fall-2024"/><category term="algorithms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jeremy Fineman]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Communication Complexity of Partial XOR Functions</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Vladimir-Podolskii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Communication Complexity of Partial XOR Functions"/><published>2024-10-24T15:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-24T15:15:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Vladimir-Podolskii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Vladimir-Podolskii/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Vladimir Podolskii October 24, 2024. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Boolean function F(x,y), where x and y are n-bit boolean vectors, is an XOR function if F(x,y) = f(x + y) for some function f on n input bits, where x+y is a bitwise XOR. XOR functions are relevant in communication complexity, partially for allowing the Fourier analytic techniques. Deterministic communication complexity of total XOR functions is relatively well understood. Montanaro and Osbourne (2009) observed that one-sided communication complexity of F is exactly equal to nonadaptive parity decision tree complexity of f. Hatami et al. (2018) showed that unrestricted communication complexity of F is polynomially related to parity decision tree complexity of f.</p> <p>In this talk we discuss the connection between communication complexity of XOR functions and parity decision trees for partial functions. We show that in case of one-sided communication complexity, whether these measures are equal, depends on the number of undefined inputs of f. More precisely, if the number of undefined points of f is small, then one-sided communication complexity of F is still equal to nonadaptive parity decision tree complexity of f. At the same time, we provide a family of examples of partial functions f with a larger number of undefined points, such that these measures are not equal. For certain values of parameters we get an exponential gap. Our separation results translate to the case of two-sided communication complexity as well, in particular showing that the result of Hatami et al. (2018) cannot be generalized to partial functions.</p> <p>Results for total XOR functions heavily rely on Boolean Fourier analysis and thus, the technique does not translate to partial functions. For the proofs of our results we build a linear algebraic framework instead. Separation results are proved through the reduction to covering codes.</p> <p>The talk is based on joint work with Dmitry Sluch and is based on the following paper: https://drops.dagstuhl.de/entities/document/10.4230/LIPIcs.ICALP.2024.116</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fall-2024"/><category term="communication"/><category term="complexity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vladimir Podolskii]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Secure Auctions for Rational Parties</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Girisha-Shankar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Secure Auctions for Rational Parties"/><published>2024-10-18T16:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T16:15:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Girisha-Shankar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Girisha-Shankar/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Girisha Shankar October 18, 2024. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Sealed bid auctions are used to allocate a resource among a set of interested parties. Traditionally, auctions need the presence of a trusted auctioneer to whom the bidders provide their private bid values. Existence of such a trusted party is not an assumption easily realized in practice. Generic secure computation protocols can be used to remove a trusted party. However, generic techniques that model security using semi-honest and malicious security models are either too weak or not efficient. It should be noted that in these models, the parties are considered to be either purely honest or purely adversarial. However, in real-life we often come across parties who take part in auctions for taking care of their own interests, that is, to maximize their own utilities. Such parties can be modeled using rational cryptography as rational agents who value winning the auction more than just learning about the bids of other parties. Moreover, these parties are often privacy sensitive, wherein they would be willing to learn about other parties’ bids only if it does not result in loss of their own privacy. Such parties are reticent to form collusion. We present protocols for running first and second price auctions in a rational cryptographic setting. We also present a novel solution concept called Privacy preserving computational dominant strategy equilibrium that can be used for modeling rational cryptographic protocols beyond the auctions.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fall-2024"/><category term="cryptography"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Girisha Shankar]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quantum approach to classical optimization: why bother and what to do?</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Jiaqi-Leng/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum approach to classical optimization: why bother and what to do?"/><published>2024-04-12T15:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T15:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Jiaqi-Leng</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/Jiaqi-Leng/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker </h3> <p>Jiaqi Leng April 12, 2024. </p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Continuous optimization problems arise in virtually all disciplines of quantitative research, including applied mathematics, computer science, and operations research. While convex optimization has been well studied in the past decades, nonconvex optimization generally remains intractable in theory and practice. Quantum computers, an emerging technology that exploits quantum physics for information processing, could pave an unprecedented path toward nonconvex optimization.</p> <p>This talk focuses on Quantum Hamiltonian Descent (QHD), a recently proposed quantum algorithm for continuous optimization. QHD is derived as the path integral of standard gradient descent (GD). It inherits the algorithmic simplicity of GD and meanwhile exhibits a drastically different behavior from GD due to the quantum interference of classical paths, especially for nonconvex optimization. Specifically, we prove that QHD can efficiently solve a family of nonconvex continuous optimization instances, each characterized by exponentially many local minima. The new mathematics of QHD, including a surprising connection between QHD and Wasserstein geometry, is yet to be understood. Beyond the standard circuit-based implementation, we also propose an analog implementation of QHD through the Hamiltonian embedding technique for sparse Hamiltonian simulation. Based on this approach, we develop an open-source software named QHDOPT, which is used in an empirical study to confirm the practical advantage of QHD for large-scale nonconvex problems.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="spring-2024"/><category term="optimization"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jiaqi Leng]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Aggregation Problems with Delay</title><link href="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/william-umboh/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Aggregation Problems with Delay"/><published>2024-01-12T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-12T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/william-umboh</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cstheory-georgetown.github.io/blog/2024/william-umboh/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speaker">Speaker</h3> <p><a href="https://williamumboh.com">William Umboh</a> January 12, 2024.</p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>In the traditional model of online algorithms, requests arrive over time and each request has to be served immediately by the algorithm on arrival. Recently, there has been a lot of interest in online problems with delay where requests can be delayed at some cost and served together in batches. In particular, the main algorithmic challenge is in balancing the delay cost and the economies-of-scale of serving requests in batches. In this talk, we will survey recent advances in a rich subclass of online problems with delay that generalize classic online problems such as TCP Acknowledgement.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="spring-2024"/><category term="distributed"/><category term="algorithms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[William Umboh]]></summary></entry></feed>